Finding Aid for the Carey McWilliams Papers LSC.1243
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Fecundity
  - Kirk, Dudley. Relations of employment levels to births in Germany. (Box 7)
  - Kiser, Clyde V., Intra-group differences in birth rates of married women. (Box 7)
  - McCleary, G.F. Prewar European population policies. (Box 7)
- Fort Romie Colony, Soledad, California
  - [No further description available]. (Box 7)
    Letter in regard to Fort Romie Colony in Factories in the field folder.
- Forward--Los Angeles
  - Forward--Los Angeles. Published in the interest of Mexican-Americans. (Box 26)
- Fresno Conference - Reports and Original Material., May 26-27th, 1939
  - Records of speeches and committee reports of Conference of state and federal agencies on agricultural labor. (Box 7)
  - Conference of state and federal agencies on agricultural labor., [Reports and other material]. (Box 7)
- Great Western Sugar Company
  - The Financial history of Great Western Sugar Company. An outline compiled by J.F. Rasmussen, Consulting Engineer for Colorado Farmers Union. (Box 7)
- Greenbelt, Maryland
  - [No further description available]. (Box 23)
    SEE: United States - Department of Agriculture - Farm Security Administration
- Haviland, Florence E.
  - Fruit tramp [and other stories] (in Migrants - Miscellaneous articles folder). Stop transient (in Migrants: federal action folder). A stop that means go in California (in Relief folder). (Box 11, 19)
- Health
  - Pamphlets and reports on health; several from Kern County. (Box 7)
    SEE: Kern County, California
- Hoadley, Walter Evans, Jr.
  - A study of one hundred seventy [?] self-resettled agricultural families, Monterey county, California, 1939, by Walter Evans Hoadley, Jr. (Box 7)
- The Hour
  - The Hour., April 30, 1939-.; 1940: no.73-77; November 30-December 28/1941: no.78-122; January 4-December 30/1942: no.122-145; January 10-November 9/1943: no.148-153; January 12-May 20/Index: no.1-75. (Box 7)
- Housing
  - Problems of a housing enforcement program, by L.M. Graves and Alfred H. Fletcher., May 1938.; Reprinted from The Journal of Land and Public Utility Economics, vol.14 no.2. (Box 8)
  - Housing in relation to public health and welfare, by Wendy Stewart. (Box 8)
  - Housing: provision of low-rent housing, by Wendy Stewart. (Box 8)
- Housing - Rural
  - Reports, newspaper clippings, etc. on housing in various parts of California. Some general reports by federal government included. (Box 8)
  - Rural households and dependency, by Olaf E. Larson. Fort Collins., 1938.; (Bulletin 444, Colorado Experiment Station). (Box 8)
  - American Society of Agricultural Engineers., February 12, 1941. (Box 8)
    A nation-wide farm building program: Immediate planning to improve farm living and working condition in difficult times ahead is highly desirable. Sant Joseph, Michigan, February 12, 1941.
- Imperial Valley, California
  - The Imperial Valley farm labor situation; report of the Special Investigating committee, Sacramento., 1934. (Box 8)
  - Clippings about labor difficulties during Pamphlet published by Associated farmers known as Phillips report: The Imperial valley situation., 1934. (Box 8)
- In Fact
  - In Fact. Long Island City, New York., 1940-1942.; vol.1 no.1-13; vol.2 no.14-23; vol.3 no.27-52; vol.4 no.53-59,61-63,65-70,72,74-75. (Box 8)
- Indians
  - [No further description available]. (Box 26)
- Indigents
  - Reports, Assembly bills, clippings on methods of treating indigents. (Box 8)
- Inter-American Affairs
  - [No further description available]. (Box 26)
    SEE: Cultural Relations
- International Juridicial Association
  - International Juridicial Association Monthly Bulletin, New York, New York., December 1938.; vol.7 no.6. (Box 8)
- Japanese
  - [No further description available]. (Box 26)
- Jews - Discrimination
  - Unbelievable, published by Friday, Incorporated. 114 E. 32nd St. New York, New York., Winter 1940.; vol.1 no.1. (Box 8)
- John Steinbeck Committee
  - Bakersfield conference on agricultural labor., October 29, 1938. (Box 20)
    Report of the Bakersfield conference on agricultural labor--health, housing and relief--held in Bakersfield, California.
- Junipero Serra
  - [No further description available]. (Box 27)
    SEE: California History (Box 26)
- Juvenile Delinquency
  - [No further description available]. (Box 27)
    SEE: Mexicans - Juvenile Delinquency (Box 29)
- Kaweah Commonwealth (The)
  - The Kaweah Commonwealth., March 14, 1891.; vol.2 no.17. (Box 6)
    (In Factories in the Field folder).
- Kaweah Co-operative Colony
  - [No further description available]. (Box 6)
    Letters, bibliography, and other material in Factories in the field folder.
- Kuplen, Louis
  - Notes on the Conference on agricultural labor of the Social Science Research Council., 1940. (Box 20)
    SEE: Social Science Research Council
- Labor Camps
  - Newspaper clippings chiefly on housing of agricultural workers. (Box 9)
- Labor Supply - Miscellany
  - Scioto Marsh. Hardin County, Ohio. (Box 10)
  - Migration and resettlement of the people, discussion by R.F. Bassey. San Francisco, National Conference on Planning., July 6-11, 1940. (Box 10)
  - Discussion of Mr. Carey McWilliams' Paper, Migration and Resettlement of People. By Walter A. Duffy. (Box 10)
  - The status of agricultural labor, by N.C. Durham. Law and Contemporary Problems, William T. Ham., October 1937; pp.559-572. vol.4 (Box 10)
  - Farm labor, by W.U. Fuhriman. Proceedings of the Western Farm Economic Association. 10th annual meeting, University of Nevada, Reno., June 24, 1937. (Box 10)
  - Letters regarding Mr. McWilliams's Farm Labor Authority Proposal. Clippings and reports on the advisability of importing Mexican labor, etc. issue of the Inter-American with Mr. McWilliams' article They Saved the Crops., August 1943 (Box 9)
  - Copy of a discussion by William E. Warne, ... of the paper on Migration and resettlement of people, by CMcW., 1940. (Box 10)
  - Distribution and seasonability of agricultural employment, by J.T. Wendzel., February 1938. (Box 10)
- Labor Supply - Press Clippings
  - Newspaper clippings on situation in California., 1942. (Box 9)
- Labor Supply - USDA Correspondence
  - Letters from Department of agriculture and other officials in regard to Mr. McWilliams' Proposal in re farm labor authority. (Box 10)
- Labor Supply and Demand
  - Letters, clippings, reports of attempts to get agricultural workers-some of them of questionable standing. (Box 10)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League
  - National Bulletin. Washington, D.C., 1940-1941.; vol.5 no.2-11,13-14; vol.5 no.1. (Box 10)
  - L.N.P.L. News: Life Preserver of Democracy. Labor's Non-Partisan League of California., March 21, 1940.; vol.1 no.1. (Box 10)
  - Pamphlet: Labor's Non-Partisan League, Its Origin and Growth. (Box 10)
    [?Sabois? Non partisan league]
- LaFollette Civil Liberties Committee
  - Statements, reports, memoranda, etc. (Box 9)
  - United States Congress, 74th. Senate Committee on education and labor. Subcommittee on Senate resolution 266. (Box 9)
    Statements, reports, memoranda, etc. prepared for or presented before the LaFollette civil liberties committee. Newspaper clippings about the hearings also included.
- Land
  - The west coast land grafters, by Bailey Millard., May 1905.; vol.12 no.5. pp.581-591. (Box 10)
  - Spanish land grant system, by R.H. Allen. Division of Land Utilization, Resettlement, Administration, Washington, D.C. (Box 10)
- Latin American Relations - Proposal
  - Proposal made to Nelson Rockefeller., 1941. (Box 27)
- Los Angeles (County) Grand Jury
  - Consideration of the question: Have citizens of Mexican descent enjoyed equal opportunity for development of good character and citizenship, (1942). (Box 27)
- Mason, Haven A.
  - A World hegemony to secure peace on earth and promote good will toward men, by Haven A. Mason. Palo Alto., 1941. (Box 10)
- McWilliams, Carey
  - Farm labor authority proposal. (Box 10)
    SEE: Labor Supply - Miscellany
  - Migration and resettlement of people, discussions of. (Box 10)
  - McWilliams, Carey - as Author. (Box 27)
- The Mears Newz
  - The Mears Newz, Mears, Michigan. (Box 27)
- Mexican-American Problems
  - General material on problems of race, background, language, etc. (Box 27)
  - Ayres, Ed Duran - Ayres Report., August 10, 1942. (Box 27)
- Mexican Campaign Notes
  - Local elections-Los Angeles and Ventura area. (Box 27)
- Mexican Labor News
  - Mexican Labor News., 1943-1944.; (incomplete). (Box 32)
    SEE: Sinarquism
- [Mexicans]
- Mexicans
  - Agnes E. Meyers articles reprinted from The Washington Post. (Box 27)
  - Arizona. (Box 27)
  - Mexicans as Imported Labor. (Box 27)
  - California. (Box 27)
  - Colorado. (Box 27)
  - Culture. (Box 28)
  - Detroit. (Box 28)
  - Discrimination. (Box 28)
  - Discrimination - Brutality and Violence. (Box 28)
  - Discrimination - Segregation in Schools. (Box 28)
  - Education. (Box 28)
  - Health. (Box 28)
  - Housing. (Box 28)
  - Juvenile Delinquency. (Box 29)
    SEE: Juvenile Deliquency
  - New Mexico. (Box 29)
  - Oregon. (Box 29)
  - Repatriation. (Box 29)
    - Silex, Humberto. (Box 29)
  - Texas. (Box 29)
  - U.S. International Relations. (Box 29)
  - Vocational Future. (Box 29)
  - War Service. (Box 29)
- Mexico - Foreign Policy
  - [No further description available]. (Box 29)
- Migrants
  - [No further description available]. (Box 29)
- Migrants - Children
  - A study of the migratory children in Kern county for the school year., 1936-1937. (Box 11)
  - Report on social problems of migrants and their families summarized. Children's Bureau, U.S. Department of Labor, Washington, D.C., August 1937.; Reprinted from the Child Monthly News Summary, vol.2 no,2. (Box 11)
  - Digest of statement by Bessie M. Knapp, Chairman of Migratory Committee, California Congress of Parents and Teachers. (Box 11)
  - Pamphlets, photostats, clippings on work of children in the fields and the lack of sufficient attendance at school. (Box 11)
  - Commission to investigate the employment of migrants., 1932. (Box 11)
    Supplement to the report of the Commission to investigate the employment of migratory children in the state of New Jersey. Trenton, MacCrelish & Quigley Company, New Jersey.
  - The child in the migratory camp - Education, by Edward J. Rowell. (Box 11)
- Migrants - Christian Science Monitor
  - Periodical clippings, by Carey McWilliams, Rex Miller, and others chiefly on problem in California. (Box 11)
- Migrants - Chronicle Articles
  - Clippings from San Francisco Chronicle chiefly on housing of migrants. (Box 11)
- Migrants - Country Gentleman
  - Articles from Country gentleman; tone more favorable to growers and Associated Framers. (Box 11)
- Migrants - Federal Action
  - Several newspaper clippings and a paper by Floence Earle Haviland: Stop transient: federal transient service for girls and boys, Los Angeles area., 1933. (Box 11)
- Migrants - Fiction
  - Two stories from New masses and one from Saturday Evening Post. (Box 11)
- Migrants - Health
  - Reports, newspaper clippings, periodical articles. (Box 11)
- Migrants - Miscellaneous Articles
  - Toward a national policy for migration, by Beecroft, Eric and Janow, Seymour., (Reprinted from Social Forces, vol.16 no.4, May 1938). (Box 11)
  - The genesis of the exodus, by Benson Y. Landis. New York, Friendship press., 31pp. (Box 11)
  - A survey of fruit and berry famers and farmers in the areas of concentrated of commercial shipments. Emergency Relief Administration., 1933-1934. (Box 14)
    This survey covered those engaged in the avocation in 1933 with various estimates for the season of 1934.
  - Farm worker bulletin, no.1., June 1938. (Box 12, Box 13)
    California conference of agricultural workers. Agricultural labor research bureau. Ameliorative proposals for agricultural labor in California in California. Berkeley, California
  - Toward a national policy for migration, by Eric Beecroft and Seymour Janow., May 1938.; Reprinted from Social Forces, vol.16 no.4 (Box 11)
  - Employment Security Review., June 1940. (Box 11)
  - Newspaper clippings, stories, articles. (Box 11)
    Stories by Florence E. Haviland including original of Fruit tramp published in Scribner's Magazine, February 1937.
  - The Genesis of the Exodus, by Benson Y. Landis. (Box 11)
    (One of five pamphlets on population shifts in America today).
- Migrants - Resettlement
  - Several pamphlets and newspaper clippings. Quite a few clippings on housing. (Box 11)
- Migratory Labor
  - I wonder where we can go now....., April 1939. (Box 13)
    A million-odd migrant farm workers and their families ask, and nobody has the answer. Underemployed, underfed, they are a national problem--most crucial in California. From Fortune Magazine.
  - Professional migratory farm labor households, by Carl F. Reuss. (Box 12)
  - The church serving the migrants, by Ethel Prince Miller. New York, Friendship Press., 1940. (Box 12)
- Migratory Labor - Arizona
  - The sanitarian's role in Maricopa County's transient labor problem, by Noel McKeehan. Sanitarian, Maricopa County Health Unit. (Box 12)
  - A survey of the migratory agricultural labor population and the program of the agricultural worker's ealth and medical association in Maricopa and Pinal counties, Arizona., November 1939. (Box 12)
- Migratory Labor - Bibliography
  - [No further description available]. (Box 12)
  - Unpublished M.A. theses on labor subjects listed by selected universities., partial list. Institute of labor studies., 1920-1940 April 1941. (Box 12)
  - Migratory farm labor; a bibliography, by Margaret Castle Schindler. University of Wisconsin., June 1929. (Box 12)
- Migratory Labor - California
  - Drought refugee and labor migration to California, June-December 1935, by Paul S. Taylor and Tom Vasey. Bureau of Labor Statistics, U.S. Department of Labor. (Box 13)
    (From the Monthly Labor Review, February 1936. Serial no.R 346).
  - Drought refugee and labor migration to California in 1936. Bureau of Labor Statistics, U.S. Department of Labor. U.S. Government Printing Office, 1937. (Box 13)
    Serial no.R 480.
  - Patterns of agricultural labor migration within California... Washington, U.S. Government Printing Office., 1938. (Box 13)
    Serial no. R 840.
  - What shall we do with them? Address before the Commonwealth Club of California, San Francisco. By Paul S. Taylor., April 15, 1938.; Clippings and notes. (Box 13)
  - Races and ethic (ethnic) groups in American life, Giannini Library., 1933.; pp.80-111. (Box 13)
  - Summary report on the background and problems affecting farm labor in California, submitted by Edward J. Rowell, Regional Labor Advisor Resettlement Administration. (Box 13)
- Migratory Labor - Colorado
  - Reports, charts, newspaper on beet workers and migratory workers in Colorado. (Box 13)
  - The people of Dolores county, Colorado: preliminary report. Texas, 1940, United States Department of agriculture - Bureau of agricultural economies. In cooperation with the Colorado agricultural experiment station. (Box 13)
  - Beet labor problems in Colorado, by R.W. Roskelley., July 10-12, 1940. (Box 13)
    A paper presented at the 13th annual meeting of the Western Farm Economics Association, Pullman, Washington and Moscow, Idaho.
- Migratory Labor - Florida
  - Study of migratory farm labor. (Box 13)
    Report of conference with representatives of the Farm Security Administration and the State Health Officer of Florida relative to...protection of the health of migratory farm laborers...
- Migratory Labor - Kern County, California
  - Reports by the Kern General Hospital, the Kern County Health Department, and Robert J. Wright on health, general conditions, and housing. (Box 13)
  - Reports by the Kern General Hospital, the Kern County Health Department, and Robert J. Wright on health, general conditions, and housing. (Box 13)
- Migratory Labor - Louisiana
  - Louisiana Council on Migratory Labor and Transients. Minutes: January 5, 1940 (8th), February 4, 1941 (11th), November 15, 1940 (10th), April 18, 1940 (9th). (Box 14)
  - Louisiana Council on Migratory Labor and Transients. Publication no.5: Why a council on Migratory Labor. (Box 14)
  - 3-A Bum, take a bow! (Box 14)
  - Louisiana Council on Migratory Labor and Transients. Labor disruptions, crowded housing in defense boom cited. (Feature article appearing in the New Orleans Item Tribune. Louisiana Council on Migratory Labor & Transients., May 18, 1941).; Publication no.6. (Box 14)
- Migratory Labor - Michigan
  - Reports on migratory sugar beet workers and migratory labor in Michigan. Correspondence. (Box 14)
  - Migratory Labor in Berrien county, by Daniel O'Connor. Michigan., March 7, 1940. (Box 14)
  - Migratory workers in Southwestern Michigan, prepared by the Intake and Certification staff in the South Haven area. Federal Works Agency, Michigan Work Project Administration, Lansing Michigan., August 12, 1940. (Box 14)
- Migratory Labor - Missouri
  - Report on the Farm Security Administration's program in Southeastern Missouri and notes. (Box 14)
  - Reports on the Southeast Missouri Project. U.S. Department of Agriculture, Farm Security Administration. (Box 14)
- Migratory Labor - Statistics
  - ...Monthly border count report... U.S. Bureau of Agricultural Economics., 1940-1942.; no.10-17, 19-24, 26. [Typed copies of December 1940-June 1941]. (Box 14, Box 15)
  - ...Persons, members of parties in need of manual employment entering Arizona and California by motor vehicle... Report... U.S. Bureau of Agricultural Economics., 1940-1942.; no.1-7, 9-10. (Box 14, Box 15)
  - ...Condensed monthly agricultural crop and labor report..., February 15, 1939-May 15, 1940. (Box 14, Box 15)
  - Report on migrants... U.S. Farm Placement Service., February 1939-December 31, 1939. (Box 14, Box 15)
- Migratory Labor - Texas
  - Texas emigrant agency law. (Box 15)
    Extract from A brief to analyze the Texas emigrant agency law and other pertinent legislation in order to clarify the exact status and obligations under the law of emigrant agencies and employment agencies; and to determine the responsibility of the Texas State Employment Service to such agencies inreferring workers to out of state employment.
  - ...Annual Report... U.S. Bureau of Employment Security. (Box 14, Box 15)
    Out of state people and returning Californians who have entered the state of California through border check stations, seeking employment....
  - Cooperative extension work in agriculture and home economics agricultural and mechanical college of Texas and United States Department of Agriculture cooperating. Extension Service, county agent work. (Box 15)
  - Reports on Migratory Labor and living conditions for migrants in Texas. General report on Migration in the Near Future. The problem of land and people. (Box 15)
- Migratory Labor - U.S.
  - A survey of labor migration between states, by N.A. Tolles. Bureau of Statistics, U.S. Department of Labor., July 1937. (Box 15)
    (From the Monthly Labor Review, serial no. R 592).
  - Memorandum re The American rural refugee problem in the west, [by Norman Littell?]. (Box 15)
  - Agricultural migratory workers in the United States of America, by Dr. Rudolf Heberle., Published in Weltwirtschaftliches Archiv vol.31, (1930 I), pp.618-640- U.C. Library H5W4 - vol.31 no.1. (Box 15)
- Migratory Labor - Washington
  - Reports on Migratory Labor. (Box 15)
  - Seasonal agricultural labor in the Yakima Valley, by Paul H. Landis., August 1937.; (From the Monthly Labor Review of the Bureau of Labor Statistics, U.S. Department of Labor. Serial no.R. 610). (Box 15)
- Migratory Workers - Miscellaneous Articles
  - California. University. Radio service. Our unwanted refugees: broadcast., February 1939. (Box 15)
  - The church and the last American migration, by Edgar E. Wilson for the Social action fellowship. California conference, M.E. church (Box 15)
- Miller, Ethel Prince
  - The church serving the migrants, by Ethel Prince Miller. New York Frienship Press., 1940. (Box 15)
    (One of five pamphlets on population shifts in American today).
- Minorites - Filipinos
  - Excerpts from report, copy of Mr. McWilliams article Exit the Filipino in The Nation, copy of article by Dr. Bogardus, Fala year book., pamphlet by Committee for the protection of Filipino rights, and other material including copies of newspapers., September 4, 1935 1940 (Box 15)
  - Philippine Commonwealth Journal Portland, Oregon., 1939-1940.; vol.1 no.3-5, vol.2 no.4. (Box 15)
  - Philippine Journal. Stockton, California., 1939-41.; vol.1 no.4, 8-10; vol.2 no.2-9, 11-16, 18-19; vol.3 no.24. (Box 15)
  - Commonwealth Times. Philippines Commonwealth Times Publication Company. 618 1/2 North Spring St., Los Angeles, California., June 1, November 15, December 1939; August 28-October 14, 1940.; vol.4 no.50-51; vol.5-62. (Box 15)
  - Commonwealth Times (Phillipines Commonwealth Times). Filipino Workers in California. P.O. Box 854 / Santa Maria, California., June 15, 1937.; vol.1 no.20. (Box 15)
- Minorities - Mexican
  - Democracy comes to cotton kingdom: the story of Mexico's la Laguna, by Clarence Senior. D.F. Centro de Estudios Pedagogicos e Hispanoamericanos., 1940. (Box 16)
  - The Mexican oil seizure, by Donald R. Richberg. New York, Standard Oil Company. [?]., 1940 (Box 16)
  - Texto vigente de la constitucion politica de los Estados Unidos Mexicanos, by Lazaro Cardenas. Ediciones pipsa. Mexico., 1939.; vol.1. (Box 16)
  - The Mexican people and the oil companies, by Alejandro Carrillo. Mexico., 1938. (Box 16)
  - New Mexico's opportunity: A message to my fellow new Mexicans, from Joaquin Ortega. Albuquerque., 1942. (Box 16)
  - Paper on the Rehabilitation for Mexican farm laborers by Joseph A. Facci and miscellaneous phamphlets and periodicals. (Box 16)
    SEE: Facci, Joseph A.
  - [No further description available]. (Box 16)
    SEE: Labor supply - Miscellany (Box 10)
  - Annual report of the Mexican Welfare Committee of the Colorado State Council, K. of C. at Denver Colorado, May 23, 1927. Fifth Annual report at Pueblo, Colorado., May 28, 1928. (Box 16)
  - Codigo agrario de los Estados Unidos Mexicanos. Mexico, Departmento de bibliotecas de la secretaria de educacion publica, (Mn.d.). Biblioteca del Obrero y Campesino, tercera edicion. (Box 16)
  - Secretaria de relaciones exteriores. Ley de nacionalidad y naturalizacion, Mexico., 1934. (Box 16)
  - Proposiciones del departmento del trabajo a la primera convercion nacional de poblacion. D.A.P.P., Mexico, 1939. (Box 16)
  - Migratory Mexican labor in Michigan. Results of conferences held with the various state departments cooperating with the Department of Labor and Industry of Michigan., 1937-1938. (Box 16)
  - Rehabilitation for Mexican Farm laborers, by Joseph A. Facci., November 18, 1939. (Box 16)
- Minorities - Miscellaneous
  - California. State commission of immigration and housing., 1918. (Box 16)
    Report on Fresno's immigration problem with particular references to educational facilities and requirements. Sacramento, California state printing office, 1918.
  - Directory of immigrant serving agencies; prepared by the Committee of Immigrant Servings Agency of the Family Welfare Council. Community Chest of San Francisco. (Box 16)
  - Hindus in the United States: their part in the economic development of the West...., by Kharaiti Ram Samras., 1936.; Also includes letter to CMcW. (Box 16)
- Monroe, Lillian
  - [Statements and articles by and about above]. (Box 16)
    SEE: The Farm Workers' Association (Box 9)
- Muir, Robert A.
  - Sacramento depression settlement survey, 1935. Submitted to the Sacramento community chest and to the Works press administration, by Robert A. Muir, supervised SERA Project 216. Sacramento., August 26, 1936. (Box 16)
- National Lawyers Guild
  - [No further description available]. (Box 29)